NATHAN L. BROUWER PHD

Data scientist specializing in complex ecological data

I am an ecological data scientist and educator with 15 years of experience extracting insights from messy data and communicating the results. I specialize in using generalized-linear mixed models (GLMMs) to analyze data from long-term observational studies. I have also taught myself key aspects of bioinformatics, phylogenetics, machine learning and population genomics. Note - All blue text is hyperlinked to relevant online materials.

RESEARCH & PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

present | 2018

Assistant Teaching Professor - General & Quantitative Biology

University of Pittsburgh Dept. of Biological Sciences

- R programming: Develop and deliver curriculum for Computational Biology course, focusing on machine learning, reproducibility, and highdimensional data (4 semesters).
- Data analysis: Instructor for Biostatistics (1 semester) and consultant on stats curriculum for lab classes.
- Science communication: Teach scientific writing, non-majors biology, intro biology lecture, Ecology & Evolution Seminar - African Ecology, and labs.

2018

Post-doctoral Research Associate - Avian Conservation National Aviary of Pittsburgh

- GLMMS: Analyzed decade-long multisite tropical bird population and community datasets.
- **Data cleaning**: Cleaned and merged diverse datasets of environmental, remote sensing and organism traits data.
- R packages: Implemented models of migratory bird populations as reproducible software.
- **Computational ecology**: Developed sensitivity and uncertainty analyses methods for for migration models.

2017 | 2016

Adjunct Professor - Biological Data Analysis

Duquesne Unv. & California Unv. of PA

• R programming & data science: Taught grad (Duq., Spring 2017) and undergrad data analyses courses (CalU, Fall 2016 and 2017).

2015 | 2009

Graduate Student

Department of Biological Sciences, University of Pittsburgh

- Graduate Research Fellow (2009-2010, 2014-2015) and NSF Pre-Doctoral Fellow (2010-2013).
- **GLMMs**: Determined appropriate model structures and analyzed data.
- **Data cleaning**: Updated, cleaned and managed data for decade-long plant demographic experiment.
- Field work: Designed and conducted research on plant demography.

CONTACT INFO

■ brouwern@gmail.com

github.com/brouwern

3 517-898-5440

EDUCATION

B.S., **Biology**, with Honors 2002. Seattle Pacific University.

Phd, Biological Sciences -Ecology & Evolution 2015. University of Pittsburgh.

SKILLS

- R packages
- GitHub
- Open Science

R programming

GLMMs (nlme, lme4, glmmTMB, brms)

GAMMs (mgcv)

Reproducible reports & pipelines

RMarkdown

Tidyverse

Data visualization with gaplot2

Scientific communication

2008 | 2009 | 2007 | 2008 | 2006 | 1 2004

2004

2002

2021

Science Writer

Quantum Scientific Publishing

 Wrote and edited customized biology materials for online charter schools.

Graduate Student / NSF Pre-Doctoral Fellow

Dept. of Zoology, Michigan State State University

 Data Cleaning: Cleaned, organized and analyzed large-scale avian community ecology dataset.

Peace Corps Volunteer - Agroforestry Outreach

National Agricultural Research Institute, The Gambia, West Africa

• Science communication: Assisted in staff development and conducted outreach on sustainable agriculture.

Infecious Disease Research Scientist

University of Washington Department of Allergy & Infectious Disease

• Lab work: Conducted experiments on pathogen cell-adhesion proteins.

■ PUBLICATIONS - SCIENCE EDUCATION

2022 • Ecology for All!

Curated compilation of Open-Access ecology resources and new content.

Gowarnis, Brouwer et. al.

- · Original content:
- Chapter 9: Ecology of Populations, section 9.1
- Chapter 10: Population modeling, sections 10.1, 10.2, and 10.4

2021 • Computational Biology for All! vs 0.9

An open access book for bioinformatics and computational biology. **Brouwer**

A Little Book of R for Bioinformatics vs. 2.0

Open-access bioinformatics primer.

Coghlan (au.) & Brouwer (ed., au)

R PACKAGES (AVAILABLE ON GITHUB)

redstart

R implementation and replication of Runge & Marra (2005) *Modeling Seasonal Interactions in the Population Dynamics of Migratory Birds*. **Brouwer** *et al.*

combio4all

A repository of functions and data useful for introductory bioinformatics and computational biology.

Brouwer & Coghlan

PASSIONS

Conservation Biology

African Ecosystems

Forest Ecology

Species Interactions

Open Science & Open data

Science Communication

PUBLICATIONS

Direct effects of a non-native invader erode native plant fitness in the forest understory

Journal of Ecology 108:189–198 Bialic-Murphy, **Brouwer** & Kaliz.

· F GLMM

•
Dryad

• Stream acidification and reduced availability of pollutionsensitive aquatic insects are associated with dietary shifts in a stream-dependent Neotropical migratory songbird.

PeerJ 6:e5141

Trevelline, Nuttle, Porter, Brouwer et al.

- **Lunsupervised Machine Learning (NMDS)**
- PeerJ Appendix

 DNA metabarcoding reveals the importance of aquatic prey subsidies and the structure of dietary niches in a community of breeding riparian songbirds.

Oecologia 187: 85-98
Trevelline. **Brouwer** *et al.*

• **Unsupervised Machine Learning** (NMDS)

Avian community characteristics and demographics reveal how conservation value of regenerating tropical dry forests changes with forest age

PeerJ 6: e5217 Latta, **Brouwer** et al.

• & GLMM, ggplot

• **GitHub**

Long-term monitoring reveals an avian species credit in secondary forest patches of Costa Rica

PeerJ 6: e3539 Latta, **Brouwer** et al.

• & GLMM, ggplot

■ Harvard Dataverse

Increased photosynthetic performance of an invasive forest herb mediated by deer overabundance

AoB Plants 9: plx011

Heberling, Brouwer & Kalisz.

- · **ℱ** GAMM
- ■ GAMM GitHub
- ■ AoB Plants

PUBLICATION TOPICS

Demographic models

Longitudinal GLMMs

Species interactions

Tropical birds

Invasive species

Treponema pallidum fibronectin-binding proteins
Journal of Bacteriology. 186:7019-7022.

Cameron, Brouwer et al.